Abraham: Employers who employ cyber
security professionals will almost
always conduct screening checks.
Just thinks about it if you are taking
someone on who is there to look after
your cyber security, wouldn’t you?
Nicole: Pre-employment or vetting
checks can help an organisation protect
itself from potential negative impact
that could happen if an employee was
taken on that might not have the best
interests of the company in mind.
There are also some legal requirements
that are necessary such as simple as
checking a candidate’s legal right to
work in the UK or more seriously whether
a criminal record prevents them from
being employed in a particular role.
Abraham: Most checks that take place are
usually related to the role a candidate
has applied for or for depending on
the organisation they want to work for.
Medical checks may be required for
a role or for insurance purposes.
Nicole: Criminal records checks
may be relevant when working with
children or in healthcare roles.
References can also check if a person
has misrepresented their previous roles.
Abraham: Many cyber security organisations
will conduct online and social media
checks to make sure that their employees’
behaviour, does not go against the
beliefs and ethics of the organisation
or will not harm it’s reputation.
Nicole: Any pre-employment checks done
must always be carried out in accordance
with data protection guidelines
according to the Data protection
Act 2018, making sure of accuracy,
relevancy, and the appropriate security.
Abraham: Any inaccuracies should
be challenged, and information
should be kept up to date.
Some checks may also need written
consent from the candidate such as
with health checks, but all employers
must make sure that they do not
discriminate by only conducting
checks on certain groups of people.
So, what are the consequences
of any unsatisfactory findings
as a result of employer checks?
Nicole: Consequences of
unsatisfactory findings can include,
not getting a job due to being
unable to get security clearance.
It can also mean a candidate not
being able to work in specific
areas or for high profile employers.
Abraham: These will always depend on
the type of check that takes place.
For example, lying on a CV about
previous roles, or not having permission
to work in the UK would likely mean
that a job offer would be withdrawn.
Nicole: For work involving finance or
the law or contact with vulnerable people
any type of unsatisfactory findings, will
usually cost the candidate a job offer.
High profile employers will not hire
those with unsatisfactory findings on any
checks as they will be concerned about
reputation and security issues and will
have to follow regulatory guidelines.
Abraham: However, saying that there
should also be a requirement on some
organisations to give an applicant chance
to explain some unsatisfactory findings
for example something that happened a
long time ago, like not paying a fine
may cause someone to have a criminal
record, but should not necessarily
be a barrier to future employment
if it does not impact their role.
Nicole: In cases like this it is
important for applicants to be upfront
and truthful about any issues that
may arise on their application, so
as not to have the role snatched away
from them at the end of the process.